hello and welcome back to real analysis and as
always first i want to thank all the nice people
that support this channel on steady or paypal
in today's part 17 we still talk about series
more concretely we will use this video and the
next ones to talk about criteria we have to check
for convergence for this please recall that a
series is just a sequence of partial sums and
in the case that this sequence is convergent we
also use this symbol to denote the limit therefore
by applying the well-known limit theorems we can
write down some properties therefore we take two
theories that need to be convergent and then
we can say something about the series that is
given by the sequence a k plus b k so here keep
in mind we have a new sequence of partial sums
now the result which is not so surprising is
that this series is also convergent we know
even more we can immediately calculate the limit
it's just given by the sum of the two limits of
course all of this is just an application of the
limit theorems you already learned for sequences
however in this case when we have convergence
theories it tells us that we can pull the addition
out of this symbol of course for a normal sum
this always works but please keep in mind this
symbol here is not a normal sum okay and another
property we get from ordinary sums is given by the
multiplication namely we have the distributive law
when we multiply all the terms in the sum with the
same factor for seris this means if the original
series is convergent then also this one no matter
which real number we choose for a lambda also here
this follows immediately from the limit theorems
and we get the calculation rule that we can
pull out lambda okay these two properties you
really should remember and you should remember
that they hold for convergent series therefore
a natural question would be how can we check that
a given series is indeed convergent in fact there
are a lot of different criteria one can apply to
answer this question the first one i want to show
you just uses the completeness axiom of the real
numbers therefore it's called the cochi criterion
please recall in the real numbers being a
convergent sequence is equivalent for being
a cauchy sequence and there the important part
was that for a crochet sequence we don't have to
know the limit therefore this criterion will check
for convergence but it does not tell you the limit
of course often this is good enough for example
if you just want to justify that you are allowed
to use these calculation rules here hence the
criterion tells us that the series is convergent
if and only if for all epsilon greater
than 0 there exists a capital n such that
for all indices n and m greater than this
capital n where also n is greater or equal
than m we have that the absolute value of the
partial sum starting with m and ending with n
is less than epsilon in other words if you can
show that this expression here is arbitrarily
small eventually then you know the series
is convergent and on the other hand if you
can show that this expression stays large or
larger than a given constant then you know the
series is not convergent okay before i show you an
example let's do the proof of this statement here
this is not so complicated because we just have
to use the completeness axiom first let's define
the partial sums as always denoted by sn then we
know the sequence sn is convergent if and only
if it is a cochise sequence that is exactly what
we know as the completeness of the real numbers
if you don't know anymore what a cauchy sequence
is let's write down the definition it just means
that for all epsilon greater zero there exists
a capital n such that for all indices afterwards
we can calculate the difference and then in the
absolute value it should be less than epsilon
here you see the indices are called untilde
and m tilde just because i want to redefine
them in the next step you already know
what we want is an expression like this
hence now you can see n should be always the
larger index here and until there i want to
shift by one hence here we get s n minus s m minus
one first you should see this is indeed a special
case of the property we had here and on the other
hand you should see it's not a restriction at all
because the only case we really miss is when we
have the same index here but of course in the case
that we have the same index there we always
get 0 out which is always less than epsilon
therefore this reformulation for a cauchy sequence
is always allowed ok now we only have to see that
this difference is exactly this sum here hence
this is the whole proof of the cochi criterion
now as promised let's apply it to an example
okay i would say let's look at the example we
had at the beginning of this course of course
we already know it's not convergent but the
question would be how can we show it with the
crochet criterion for this we have to calculate
this partial sum here now you already know we
only need to calculate this for indices nm that
are greater or equal than some capital n therefore
maybe let's substitute the m with the capital n
in other words we look at the special case for m
and we can do the same for n for example it would
be allowed to choose n plus 2. therefore
the sum consists of exactly three numbers
and of course we can calculate
them we just have to distinguish
two different cases the first case would be n
is even then we have one plus minus one plus one
therefore for an even n we get out one for the
sum of course then the absolute value does not
change anything okay then the other case would
be an odd n which means we start with minus one
then comes one and then we add minus one again
hence the result is minus one but with the
absolute value it's one as well hence no matter
what n is this expression is always exactly 1
which is of course not less than epsilon if
we choose epsilon less than 1. in conclusion
this property here can't be fulfilled for all
epsilon indeed now this is all we have to do
to show that this series is not convergent so here
you see the cochi criterion as simple as it is
can be very helpful in calculations and it is also
very helpful for showing the next important fact
maybe in this example you have already seen
there is a necessary condition for being a
convergent series just take any sequence of real
numbers ak and look at this series and if this
is convergent you know the sequence ak
has to be a sequence that converges to 0.
ok here you see the contraposition to this is
if you start with a sequence a k that is not
convergent to 0 the series we get out is divergent
and of course here you see immediately one example
where you can apply this fact minus 1 to the
power k is not a convergent sequence at all
however one important thing to note
here is this is not an equivalence
please remind yourself in the last video we
have already seen a counter example for this
now i can tell you this proof works similarly
to the things we did in the example above
therefore i think this is a good exercise for
you try to prove this fact afterwards then you
know every time someone asks you about series and
the convergence of it you should check this thing
here first however of course most of the time you
still don't know if the series is convergent then
in this case you have to apply another criterion
and such another one i show you in the next video
therefore i hope i see you
there and have a nice day bye
you